片名：血色将至
1898年
不！
No!
找到她了，找到她了…
There she is. There she is.
终于找到了
There she is.
新墨西哥，恩格尔   - 渣化试金银法
1902年
女士们先生们
Ladies and gentlemen,
我穿越了半个州，今晚来到这里
I've traveled over half our state to be here tonight.
我本该早些过来，但由于   我在野狼山的新油井刚开始出油
I couldn't get away sooner because my new well was coming in
有些事要安排，一时间脱不开身
at Coyote Hills and I had to see about it.
那口井现在的出油量是两千桶…
That well is now flowing at 2,000 barrels
每周都能给我带来五千美金收入
and it's paying me an income of $5,000 a week.
我在别处还有两支勘探队   在羚羊谷有十六口产油井
I have two others drilling and I have 16 producing at Antelope,
所以说，如果我自称是一名油矿主   你们应该不会反对
so, ladies and gentlemen, if I say I'm an oilman, you will agree.
你们现在面对的机会绝佳…
Now, you have a great chance here,
但别忘了，如果疏忽大意   到头来可能会一无所获
but bear in mind you could lose it all if you're not careful.
也许有很多人在想租你们的地，钻井探油
Out of all men that beg for a chance to drill your lots,
但20个人里面，可能只有一个是油矿主
maybe one in twenty will be oilmen.
其余的家伙都是些投机分子
The rest will be speculators,
他们只想当矿主租地生意的中介人
that's men trying to get between you and the oilmen
将应属于你们的部分财富攫为己有
to get some of the money that ought, by rights, come to you.
即便你们找到个有钱又肯钻井的主
Even if you find one that has money and means to drill,
多半是个对钻探一无所知的门外汉
he'll maybe know nothing about drilling.
这种人通常会把项目转托给承包商
He'll have to hire the job out on contract,
你们的命运也押在了承包商手上…
and then you're depending on a contractor,
而承包商往往应付一下就早早收工
who'll rush the job through
用省出的时间换新的一份承包合同
so he can get another contract just as quick as he can.
我们这一行的规则就是如此
This is the way that this works.
- 那你肯给我们多少？   - 我们在浪费时间
What is your offer? We're wasting time.
请安静！
Please!
我亲自负责钻探…
I do my own drilling.
凡是为我工作的，只有我一个老板   每个工人我都了如指掌
And the men that work for me, work for me, and they are men I know.
我会把办公室搬到钻探现场   实地视察手下的工作
I make it my business to be there and to see their work.
我的人不会笨到把工具掉到井里   然后再花几个月在摸找工具上面
I don't lose my tools in the hole and spend months fishing for them.
也不会愚蠢地凿穿固井层
I don't botch the cementing off
白白让渗水毁了整口油井
and let water in the hole and ruin the whole lease.
我是一个家庭观念很重的男人
I'm a family man.
把钻井开油当成家族产业在做   这是我的儿子兼合伙人H.W. 普莱维
I run a family business. This is my son and my partner, H.W. Plainview.
我们的理念是，大伙在一起就是一家人   虽然很少有油矿主能认同这种理念
We offer you the bond of family that very few oilmen can understand.
有一点我与其他同行都不一样   我打算在此处扎根，长期采油
I'm fixed like no other company in this field
因为我的野狼山油井已开始出油
and that's because my Coyote Hills well has just come in.
我拥有成套的钻探工具   可随时投入工作
I have a string of tools all ready to put to work.
我在别处的钻井设备可立即装车   一周内就能运达这里
I can load a rig onto trucks and have them here in a week.
我有许多贸易伙伴   能搞到搭建井架的木料
I have business connections, so I can get the lumber for the derricks.
只有靠朋友办事才会有这种速度
Such things go by friendship in a rush like this.
所以我才敢在这儿和你们拍板   不仅可以立即开工
And this is why I can guarantee to start drilling
还能拿出充足的资金   以证明我所言非虚
and to put up the cash to back my word.
女士们先生们，我向你们保证
I assure you, ladies and gentlemen,
其他人不管说得如何天花乱坠
no matter what the others promise to do,
当万事俱备，只等开工的时候   他们就一个个地不见人影了
when it comes to the showdown, they won't be there.
坐下！坐下，你不能…
Sit down! Sit down, you have no right...
让我们谈谈最重要的话题
Let us discuss what the man has to say.
- 普雷斯科特，你相信他么？   - 让我们谈谈最重要的话题
- Prescott, do you trust this man? - Let's discuss what he has to say.
- 他说的在理   - 他怎么知道？那是我的地！
- There's logic to what he's saying. - How does he know? My lot is there!
他说两到三年，也许是十年！
Two or three years, it could be ten years!
- 到头来一场空！   - 可他刚开了一口油井！
- We gain nothing by losing our heads! - Look at that well out there!
没人会一场空
Nobody's losing their heads.
你在这儿又没生意！
You have no business being here!
让那个女的坐好，先生！
Sit that woman down, sir!
你坐下
You can sit down.
普莱维先生！请留步，普莱维先生
Mr. Plainview! Please, Mr. Plainview.
不，普莱维先生，你要去哪儿？
No, Mr. Plainview! No, where are you going?
- 谢你好意，但我不想签约了   - 但我们需要你！
- I don't need the lease. Thank you. - But we need you.
不同的意见太多了   耽误你时间了
Too much confusion. Thank you for your time.
不不不，我们没有不同意见
No, no, there's no confusion.
即使现在把开采权白送给我   我也不会在租约上签字的
I wouldn't take the lease if you gave it to me as a gift.
班克塞先生，我不想浪费您的时间
Mr. Bankside, I'm not going to waste your time.
希望您也别浪费我的时间
I'd certainly appreciate it if you didn't waste mine.
如果与我签了合同   十天内就可以开始钻井
Now, if you wish to sign with me, we can have a well drilling within 10 days.
您的土地位于出油点的北面较远处
Your lot is further north from the discovery well up here.
这意味着可能要挖得更深才能见油
That means we'll probably have to dig deeper.
如果不出在下所料…
And if there's as much oil here as I think there is,
在您那儿找油会更加困难一些   但只要找到油，开采不成问题
it'll be harder to reach, but once we find it, we can take it right out.
我们必须得加快行动，否则过不多久   这片地区的石油就会被开采殆尽的
We have to act quickly, because very soon these fields will be dry.
希望你们快做决定
I need you to know what you want to do.
由于距离石油发现点较远…
Now, because of the distance from the discovery well,
你的收益分成将比预计的少一些
I'll pay you a smaller royalty than you'd get down there
但我愿多付您一千美元作征地补偿
but I'm prepared to give you a $1,000 bonus on your lot.
你说的收益分成是多少？
What kind of royalty are you talking about?
六分之一，外加十天内开工保证
One-sixth, plus a guarantee to start drilling within 10 days.
没有比这更公道的价钱了
Now, that's something you won't find anywhere else.
夫人，你的孩子几岁了？
What age are your children, ma'am?
一个十岁，另一个十二
Ten and twelve.
我有个问题，普莱维先生   您的夫人呢？
Mr. Plainview, a question, sir. Where is your wife?
班克赛夫人，她死于难产
She died in childbirth, Mrs. Bankside.
现在只剩我们父子两个了
So it's just me and my son now.
老板，出油了！
It's coming in, boss!
听这声音！
Hear it?
普莱维先生？
Mr. Plainview?
哪位？
Yes?
您就是丹尼尔·普莱维？
Are you Daniel Plainview?
是我
Yes.
能为你效劳么？
What can I do for you?
您在找石油？
You look for oil.
没错
That's right.
如果一个地方有油   您愿为此付多少钱？
What do you pay for a place that has it?
- 要看情况了   - 看哪些情况？
- Well, that depends. - What does it depend on?
有许多因素
On a lot of things.
如果我知道哪块地方有油   而且那儿的地价又很便宜
If I told you I knew a place that had oil where land could be bought cheaply,
您认为这个情报值多少钱？
what do you think that would be worth?
你得让我先了解你都知道些什么
I think that you should let me know what you know
然后我们再慢慢谈
and then we'll try and work something out.
- 我能坐下么？   - 请坐吧
- Can I sit down? - Please.
请问您是哪个教派的？
What church do you belong to?
我么…
I...
各种信仰我都不排斥…   也没有特别确定的教派
I enjoy all faiths. I don't belong to one church in particular.
所有教派我都喜欢…我热爱一切   你从哪儿来？
I like them all. I like everything. Where are you from?
我一会儿告诉你   这也是我要卖给你的情报
That would be telling you. That's what I want to sell you.
你在信号山这儿干什么工作？
What are you doing in Signal Hill?
我们那儿的油，多得都渗出地面了
We have oil, and it seeps through the ground.
想知道在哪儿么？付点钱给我吧
Do you want to pay me to know where it is?
光是地表冒油…
Just 'cause there's something on the ground
并不代表地底下有油
doesn't mean there's anything beneath it.
那为何标准石油公司要在我们那儿   大肆收购土地？
Why did Standard Oil buy up land?
你说的地方在加利福尼亚？
Is it in California?
- 也许在   - 他们买下了多少土地？
- Maybe. - How much land did they buy?
希望你不是在怀疑我的智商   那样我会好受一点
I'd like it better if you didn't think I was stupid.
你为什么来找我？
Why did you come to me?
- 因为你在这儿的油井出油了   - 说的也是
- You just brought this well in. - That's right.
好吧，要不这样， 你给我500元
Yes, so just give me $500 in cash right now
我就把我知道的地方告诉你
and I'll tell you where it is.
年轻人，我的想法是这样的   我先给你100元…
I'll tell you what I'll do, son. I'll give you $100 now,
如果那块地方真的有利可图   我再奖给你1000元
and if it proves to be a promising lease, then give you a $1,000 bonus.
先给我600元
Six hundred dollars.
为了帮助判断，告诉我一件事情   你们那儿有些什么？
Tell me one thing to help me decide. What else have you got up there?
种着什么作物？
What do you grow?
是一片大牧场，但大部分都是石地
We have a big ranch, but it's mostly rocks.
除了野草，种什么都没收成
Plant things. Nothing will grow but weeds.
你认为上面能长什么？
What makes you think it's up?
那附近有硫磺或盐碱矿么？
Is there sulfur around? Or alkali deposits?
有盐碱矿，硫磺是什么我不清楚
Alkali nearby. I don't know sulfur.
那是你儿子？
Is that your son?
是的
Yes.
- 你好   - 你好
- Hi. - Hi.
- 请问您是哪位？   - 我叫弗莱彻·哈密尔顿
- Who are you? - I'm Fletcher Hamilton.
很高兴认识你，年轻人   你叫什么名？
Nice to meet you, son. What's your name?
你是干什么的？
What do you do?
我为普莱维先生工作
I work with Mr. Plainview.
这是500美金
Here's $500, son.
再说点有用的，这钱就给你
You tell me something worth hearing, this money's yours.
我来自伊莎贝拉郡的小波士顿镇
I come from a town called Little Boston in Isabella County.
我们在这里   这里是小波士顿的马刺火车站
This is us, here. Spur station here at Little Boston.
你们要找的是桑迪农场
The Sunday ranch is what you're looking for.
你们可以顺着这条放羊道走
There's a sheep trail that takes you there.
出镇往西走一英里，不是很远的地方
It's a mile out of town headed west, not far.
穿过山脚下的这个小小隘口
Just through a small pass here near the base of the hills.
再经过一座教堂   然后顺着放羊道走就到了
You'll pass a church and just follow the sheep trail.
- 标准石油公司买了哪几块地？   - 这儿，还有这儿
- Where's Standard buying up? - Here and here.
- 你的家人姓桑迪？   - 是的
- Your family name is Sunday, yes? - That's right.
家里有几口人？
How many's in your family?
我父母，几个姐妹，还有我兄弟伊莱
My father and mother and sisters and my brother Eli.
- 你有几个姐妹？   - 两个
- How many sisters do you have? - Two.
- 你叫什么？   - 保罗
- What's your name? - Paul.
你家人知道那儿附近有石油么？
Does any of your family know about the oil that you say is there?
我不清楚
I don't know.
我叔叔常说附近有油
My uncle always said there was oil there,
但我不知道其他人听说过没有
but I don't know what they heard or what they think.
你们种些什么？
What do you grow?
养了些羊，是个放羊的牧场   我说过，那儿除了野草什么都不长
lt's goats. It's a goat farm. I told you, nothing grows but weeds.
- 有水源么？   - 有，但水质很咸
- Is there water? - It's salty.
打井取水，很少能取到不咸的水
You drill a well, it's hard not to get saltwater.
我敢肯定，那儿有石油
The oil is there. I'm telling you.
- 我要走了，那么……   - 今晚就住这里好了
- I want to go now, so... - You can stay tonight.
- 不，我想走，我得离开这里   - 听着，保罗
- No, I want to go now. I want to leave. - Listen, Paul.
假如我大老远跑到那儿   结果发现你是在说谎…
If I travel all the way out there and I find that you've been lying to me,
我会抓到你，让你吐出更多的钱
I'm going to find you and I'm going to take more than my money back.
你觉得这样可以么？
Is that all right with you?
- 可以，先生   - 那就这样吧
- Yes, sir. - All right, then.
- 祝您好运，愿主保佑你   - 你也一样，年轻人
- Nice luck to you. God bless. - And to you, young man.
- 有人过来了   - 谢谢，玛丽
- There's someone coming. - Thank you, Mary.
- 晚上好   - 晚上好
- Good evening. - Good evening.
我叫丹尼尔·普莱维   这是我儿子HW
My name's Daniel Plainview. This is my son, H.W.
- 你们来打猎么？   - 来猎鹌鹑
- Are you hunting? - Hunting for quail.
先前听别人说桑迪农场附近   有块地方适合露营
We're told there might be a good place to camp up near the Sunday ranch.
这儿就是桑迪农场   你们可以在这里露营
This is the Sunday ranch. You can camp here.
- 谢谢你，有水么？   - 有的
- Thank you. Do you have water? - Yes.
听说这儿几天前发生了地震
We heard there was an earthquake up here a few days ago.
- 是真的么？   - 是的
- Is that right? - Yes.
- 你家人好么？   - 他们都好，谢谢关心
- Your family? - Yeah, all fine. Thank you.
- 如果不介意，我们有羊奶   - 那样也好
- We have goat's milk, if you'd like. - That would be fine.
那么
Now,
如果我们把帐篷扎在那儿   就不会挡你们的路了
if we set our tent away over there, we'd be out of your way over there.
没问题
That's fine.
露丝，来帮忙，带点水过来
Ruth! Help these men and bring them some water.
不用！H.W你去
No! H.W.
普莱维先生，要不要现在来点羊奶？
Mr. Plainview, would you like that milk now?
- 好的，谢谢   - 玛丽，拿点羊奶来
- That would be fine. Thank you. - Mary! Bring them some milk.
我家人会帮你扎帐篷的
My family will help you set up your tent.
不用了，谢谢   我们一路上都是自己动手的
No, please. We set ourselves on this camping trip.
我们得自己扎营
We have to do the camping.
快点！
Hurry up!
- 有面包么   - 只有土豆
- Do you have bread? - We have potatoes.
土豆也可以，谢谢你
Potatoes would be nice, thank you.
我让她们去把土豆煮好
I'll have them boil you up some potatoes.
没关系，我们可以自己烤
That's all right. I thought maybe we'd make a fire.
我准备带儿子一起生堆篝火
I wanted to work with my son on making a fire.
那好，我儿子伊莱会送柴火来的
All right. My son, Eli, will bring you some wood.
谢谢盛情款待   您是桑迪先生？
Thank you so much for your hospitality, Mr. Sunday.
- 是的   - 我们不会妨碍你们的
- Yes. - And we'll be out of your way.
- 只是来打鹌鹑的   - 好的
- We're just hunting for quail. - Yes.
- 很抱歉，面包没有了   - 不，没关系
- I'm sorry we don't have any bread. - No, no, no.
这山头种不了粮食，到处都是石头…
Corn doesn't fill out in the hills here. It's mostly rock.
连块像样的粮食地也没有
We don't have room to raise the grain.
谢谢你，年轻的小姐
Thank you, young lady.
我叫伊莱
My name is Eli.
你就是伊莱·桑迪吧
Yes, you're Eli Sunday.
欢迎您来这儿
Welcome.
- H.W   - 伊莱
- H.W. - Eli.
- 你们来猎鹌鹑？   - 是的
- You're hunting quail? - That's right.
- 我们会送晚饭过来的   - 谢谢，太感谢你们了
- We will bring dinner. - Thank you. Thank you so much.
爸爸！
Dad!
爸爸，看我的鞋子
Dad, look at my shoe.
这些石油是因为地震才冒出来的   我们走
That's earthquake oil. Set loose.
这么说…
So...
怎么说？
So?
这么说的话…
So, so.
如果这底下藏着油，可以把它往海边运
If there's anything here, we take it to the sea.
我们要做的就是建一条输油管线   终点是韦尼缪港或圣保拉
What we do is we build a pipeline to Port Hueneme or Santa Paula,
总长大约100英里
it's about 100 miles,
然后把油卖给联合石油公司   我们要做的就是这些
and we do a deal with Union Oil. This is what we do.
这样就不需要铁路了   也不必在货运上花钱了
Then we don't need the railroads and their shipping costs anymore.
你明白吗？
You see?
明白了
Yeah.
- 全都明白了？   - 是的
- You see that? - Yeah.
然后我们就坐等收钱吧   真金白银滚滚而来…
Then we're making money. We're making the real money.
每个硬币都落入我们的腰包
What we should be making. Not just...
无需再把钱浪费在运输上了
Not just throwing it away on shipping costs.
不然的话，就剩不下几个钱了
Otherwise, it's just mud.
我们要付给他们多少钱？
How much are we going to pay them?
哪个他们？
Who's that?
桑迪一家
The Sunday family.
我们不用石油的名义买
I'm not going to give them oil prices.
我们用鹌鹑的名义买
I'll give them quail prices.
占用您几分钟时间
If we could take a few minutes,
有件事情很想和您谈谈
there's something I'd very much like to talk with you about.
孩儿他妈，把姑娘们带出去
Mother, would you take the girls outside, please?
我喜欢直话直说
I believe in plain speaking, so...
您的农场很漂亮   我很喜欢猎鹌鹑
This is a beautiful ranch. I love hunting for quail.
你知道，我儿子身体不太好   他需要多呼吸新鲜空气
My boy has been sick, you know. He needs fresh air.
看过的医生都说   最好让他生活在空气清新的地方
Doctors all say he needs plentiful fresh air.
所以…
So,
埃布尔，你认为这块地卖多少钱合适？
what would you say would be a fair price for this lot, Abel?
- 你要买下这地方？   - 说得没错
- To buy this place? - That's right.
不急，慢慢想
Take a moment.
- 我不知道该卖多少   - 每英亩六美元
- I'm sorry. I don't know. - Six dollars an acre.
六美元？谢谢你开价，伊莱
Six dollars? Thank you, Eli.
这几年装修农场花了不少钱   大概500美元的样子…
And then with the improvements to the ranch over the years at $500...
我愿出3700美元买下这片农场
I'd like to offer you $3,700 for this ranch.
- 一共3700美元   - 不行
- That's $3,700. - No.
伊莱，这个人是上帝派来的啊
The Lord has sent this man here, Eli.
是的，我也相信是上帝让我来的
Yes, I believe He has.
- 我给你们的报价是3700美元   - 究竟是什么让你来这里的，先生？
- My offer to you is $3,700. - What is it that brought you here, sir?
是上苍神意的指引
The Good Lord's guidance.
- 当然，除了神意之外…   - 我们的石油呢？
- Now, of course, within that... - What about our oil?
…我们还得签一份合同
...we're going to develop a lease.
- 你说什么？   - 我们的石油呢？
- What's that? - What about our oil?
什么石油？
What about it?
我们这儿有石油，应该值不少钱
We have oil here. That's worth something.
你能组织人钻探么？
Do you have someone who can drill for it?
- 你认为这儿有石油？   - 我知道这儿有
- Do you think there's oil here? - I know there is.
要钻探石油得花很多钱
It's very expensive to drill.
把油从地底下取出来是大工程   你之前有没有试过自己开采？
To get it up and out of the ground. You ever tried that before?
- 要花多少钱？   - 很多钱
- How much is it? - Costly.
但是，这儿的油埋得很浅
Well, our oil sits right up on top of the ground.
我相信你看到的是渗油
I believe that's called seepage.
这并不代表下面藏着石油
Doesn't necessarily mean there's anything underneath.
- 为此你准备出多少钱？   - 我没想过
- What would you give us for it? - I don't know.
- 这事你竟然没想过？   - 是的，没错
- Something you don't know. - That's right.
你想要多少，伊莱？
What would you like, Eli?
一万美金
Ten thousand dollars.
为了什么？
For what?
为了我的教堂
For my church.
说得不错
That's good.
这是个好理由
That's a good one.
好罢…
Well...
如果我们决定在此开采石油   如果此地真能产油
If we decide to drill for oil and if the well begins to produce,
我会给你的教堂捐5000美元
I'll give your church a $5,000 signing bonus.
一万美元
Ten thousand.
你想去找别人来钻探么？ 伊莱？
Do you want to find someone else that's going to come here and drill, Eli?
投入资金，还要自己出工出力…
Make the investment and do all the hard work that goes into it?
我大可以找一处别的农场   在那儿安安静静的猎鹌鹑
I can just as easily hunt for quail on another ranch as I can here, so...
但我也很乐意尽全力支持你的教堂
Though I'll happily be a supporter of your church for as long as I can.
前提是这儿真的有石油
For the bonus only.
假如真有油的话   我倒是有些钻探行当的熟人…
Now, as it happens, I do have some connections in the drilling business
到时候能帮我们做些采油的事情   你觉得怎么样，埃布尔？
who might help get us started. How do you feel about this, Abel?
我没意见，听伊莱的就行
Yes. What Eli says.
好吧，那这样，先签几份合同
Well, good! Let's draw up some contracts and let's...
我们一起试试看
Let's give it a try.
感谢你的协助，伊莱
Appreciate your help with this, Eli.
- 下午好   - 下午好
- Good afternoon. - Good afternoon.
- 土地管理局？   - 是的
- Real estate? - Yes.
我找您有事
Yes, I'd like to talk to you.
我想找几块地，我刚买了桑迪农场
I'm looking for some land. I just bought the Sunday ranch.
然后…呃，能看下地图么？
And, well, where's the map?
桑迪农场后面的丘陵在哪儿？
Where are the hills behind the Sunday ranch?
在这儿，这块土地属于班迪   一共六百多英亩
That's here. It's the Bandy tract. He has over 600 acres.
班迪，六百…
Bandy, 600.
- 那这块地方呢？   - A.C·莫德、布罗基特、雷德利克、卡尔…
- What about this? - A.C. Maude, Blodget, Redlick, Carr.
- 地价多少？   - 每英亩六美元
- What's it held at? - Six dollars an acre.
六美元…
Six.
这儿呢？
What about this?
是贝尔文的地，买下应该没问题   我敢肯定
That's the Belvins, and that could be got, I'm sure.
这儿附近的土地都能买到手么？
Can everything around here be got?
是的，肯定
Sure.
保罗·桑迪曾是我们的好朋友
Paul Sunday turned out to be a good friend of ours.
没错
That's right.
你快点过来吧   叫弗雷德·英吉利一起来
Well, you get here just as soon as you can. Bring Fred English.
好，就这样
Good enough.
谢谢你，师傅
Thank you, porter.
- H.W.，你好么？   - 很好，您呢？
- H.W., how are you? - Fine, and you?
- 还不错，你爸呢？   - 他在里面
- Pretty good. Where's your dad? - He's inside.
你们大老远从希格诺山到这儿来…
You fellas are a long way from Signal Hill.
- 你好啊，普莱维   - 你好，吉恩
- Hello, Plainview. - Hello, Gene.
- 很高兴见到你   - 你好查理
- Good to see you. - Charlie.
- 这是赶着去哪儿？   - 顺路经过这里，就下来看看
- On your way somewhere else? - Passing through. Looking around.
- 你也在这儿，真奇怪啊   - 是啊，我也觉得奇怪
- Funny to see you. - Funny, isn't it?
你的人又在忙家族产业了
You boys are a regular family business.
你的人这次迟到了
You boys are a little late.
- 你发现了什么？   - 一些有趣的东西
- What did you find? - I found some interesting prospects.
听说标准石油在此购地了么？
Did you hear Standard bought up?
- 他们现在买的地皮大多在镇子北面   - 我也听人这么说
- Mostly in the north, so far. - That's what I hear.
跟你说，吉恩，如果你也想加入   从镇东面开始吧…
I'm gonna tell you, Gene, if you're gonna make a play, look east.
早晚别人会来，我宁愿那人是你   你脚下的这片土地已名花有主了
I'd rather it be you than someone else. This mud around here has been taken.
身边带着个俏脸蛋   每天的阳光都灿烂啊
It must be easy when you have such a cute face to carry around with you.
- 你想夸我儿子英俊？   - 就算我是好了
- Telling me how handsome my son is? - Well, that I am.
真动听，谢谢夸奖   祝你好运，吉恩
That's very nice. Thank you. Good luck, Gene.
- 多保重   - 听我的话，去东面看看
- Take care. - Like I said, go east.
H.W.
如果你需要签合同，我愿当你的律师
I'll be your lawyer if you need to draw up a contract.
以免你上人家的当   你老爸赚的钱也该有你一半
Make sure you don't get swindled, boy. Get half what your dad's making.
这儿怎么样?
How's that?
那些人在做什么？
What are those men doing?
他们为我们工作
They're just guys that are working for us.
他们只是在这儿四处看看
They're just looking around.
我们能赚多少钱？
How much money can we make?
我不知道，要看情况了
I don't know. It depends.
一千美元？
One thousand dollars?
玛丽说如果她不祷告，她爸会揍她
Mary said that her father beats her if she doesn't pray.
玛丽，是那个最小的女儿？
Mary, she's the smaller one?
是的
Yes, she is.
- 人都到齐了？   - 基本顺利
- Everyone here? - Very successful.
但是…？
But?
只有一个人，他名下的地产尚无着落
There were a few vacant lots and one holdout.
- 谁？   - 威廉·班迪
- Who? - William Bandy.
一共八块地…他什么来头？
...eight. Who's he?
是个老头，在此定居
He's an old man who homesteaded here.
他和孙子一起住   他有话要和你说
Lives with his grandson. He said he'd like to speak with you.
他来了么？
Is he here?
没来，他希望你亲自上门拜访
No, he'd like you to come visit with him.
他想抬价？
He's boosting his price.
他说想和买地的人谈谈
He said he'd like to speak with whoever is doing the buying.
那就让他等着吧   下次他自己会来的，我们走
Well, let him wait. He'll come around. Let's go.
女士们，先生们…
Ladies and gentlemen?
女士们，先生们
Ladies and gentlemen.
谢谢你们今晚能来到这儿
Thank you so much for visiting with us this evening.
我穿越了半个州   最后把目光投在这片土地上
Now, I've traveled across half our state to be here and to see about this land.
你们中有些可能已经听说了…
Now, I daresay some of you might have heard
某些有关本人计划的无边传闻
some of the more extravagant rumors about what my plans are,
我想在此亲自道明事实的真相
so I just thought you'd like to hear it from me.
大家面对面，没什么神秘的
This is the face. It's no great mystery.
女士们先生们，我是一个油矿主
I'm an oilman, ladies and gentlemen,
我在本州有许多产业
I have numerous concerns spread across this state.
我的油井群每日出产几千桶原油
I have many wells flowing at many thousand barrels per day,
因此我自认是一名油矿主
so I like to think of myself as an oilman.
作为一名油矿主
As an oilman, I hope that you'll forgive
我这人向来有话直说，请各位见谅
just good old-fashioned plain speaking.
这个行当对我来说，是家族产业
Now, this work that we do is very much a family enterprise.
我的好儿子H.W和我并肩作战
I work side by side with my wonderful son, H. W.
你们中有些人可能见过他
I think one or two of you might have met him already.
我还鼓励手下也将家人带在身边
And I encourage my men to bring their families, as well.
有家人陪伴，生活也变得更有滋味
Of course, it makes for an ever so much more rewarding life for them.
成家了就会有孩子   有孩子就该有教育
Family means children, and children means education.
所以不管我们在哪儿落脚   教育都是必不可少的
So, wherever we set up camp, education is a necessity,
我也很乐意为孩子提供教育的机会
and we're just so happy to take care of that.
我要在小波士顿建一流的学校
So let's build a wonderful school in Little Boston.
孩子就是我们为之奋斗的未来
These children are the future that we strive for,
他们理当拥有最好的东西
and so they should have the very best of things.
现在，我还要说一件事
Now, something else,
请恕我冒犯…我要说的是面包
and please don't be insulted if I speak about this. Bread.
让我们谈谈面包吧
Let's talk about bread.
我印象中，在这个伟大的国家里
Now, to my mind, it's an abomination to consider
任何男人，女人或是小孩子   如果把一块面包当作奢侈品
that any man, woman, or child in this magnificent country of ours
将是多么的可悲
should have to look upon a loaf of bread as a luxury.
我们可在此地挖水井   有了淡水，就能灌溉
We're going to dig water wells here, and water wells means irrigation.
有了灌溉，就能种粮食
Irrigation means cultivation.
那些曾经的不毛之地将变成良田沃野
We're going to raise crops here where before it just simply wasn't possible.
等到收获季节，粮食多得发愁
You're going to have more grain than you'll know what to do with,
这位女士，你家的面包会堆得淹过脖子
and bread will be coming right out of your ears, ma'am.
修建道路，发展农业   提供就业，兴办教育…
New roads, agriculture, employment, education.
这只是我们建设计划中的寥寥几项而已
These are just a few of the things we can offer you,
女士们先生们，我向你们保证
and I assure you, ladies and gentlemen,
如果在这里找到了石油…
that if we do find oil here,
我觉得此事为真的可能性很大
and I think there's a very good chance that we will,
你们不但能在此地继续繁衍   这片家园还将更加兴旺富强
this community of yours will not only survive, it will flourish.
如果有什么问题尽管向我提…   什么问题？
I'd be happy to answer any questions that you might have. Yes?
新辟的道路通往教堂么？
Will the new road lead to the church?
教堂将会是新路的第一站   谢谢你伊莱，还有问题么？
That'll be the first place that it leads. Thank you, Eli. Anyone else?
那好，如果有其他疑惑   我会一直恭候大驾光临
Well, if anything comes up, I'm pretty easy to find.
到时尽管来找我
You just come visit with me.
谢谢你们今晚的参与，晚安
Thank you so much for your time, and good night.
“这是我们的特权…
What a privilege to carry
“用祈祷向神祝愿…
everything to God in prayer!
这是我们的特权…”
What a privilege to carry...
顺着新路走就能到教堂了
Just follow the new road right to the church.
顺着新路走就不会走错
The new road will lead you there.
你好，兄弟，我叫伊莱
Hello, brother, my name is Eli.
第三启示教会欢迎您光临   (第一启示为摩西十诫；第二为耶稣临世   预言中还有第三次末日启示，尚未发生)
The Church of the Third Revelation welcomes you.
你好，兄弟，我叫伊莱
Hello, brother, my name is Eli.
第三启示教会欢迎您光临
The Church of the Third Revelation welcomes you.
顺着新路走就能到教堂了.
Just follow the new road right to the church.
“耶稣知道世人的罪
Jesus knows our every weakness
“真心祈祷向神忏悔
Take it to the Lord in prayer
“我们脆弱又疲惫
Are we weak and heavy-laden
“他人关切成累赘
Cumbered with a load of care?
“救世主给了我们安慰
Precious Savior still our refuge
真心祈祷向神忏悔…”
Take it to the Lord in prayer...
- 能和你说几句么，丹尼尔？   - 可以，请进吧
- Daniel, may I speak with you? - Yes, come in.
等他们到了，我就带过来
I'll bring them up when they arrive.
- 早上好   - 早上好
- Good morning. - Good morning.
工作进展怎么样？
How is all the work coming?
都很顺利
Everything's good.
- 所有工人都已就位？   - 当然
- All the men are provided for? - Of course.
士气好像很高昂啊
Spirits seem high.
需要我为你们做什么嘛？
Is there anything that you need from me?
- 需要教会做什么嘛？   - 我想还没有，谢谢你
- Anything the church can do for you? - I don't believe so. No. Thank you.
听说你让众人明天到这儿集合…
I understand you've asked the people to gather around
一起参加油井开工仪式，有这回事么？
and watch the well begin tomorrow. Is that right?
- 有这么回事   - 我会为油井祈福的
- That's right. - I will bless the well.
在仪式开始前，把我介绍给大家
Before you begin, you should introduce me.
然后我会走到油井那里…
You'll see me walk up towards the oil well, and when I...
是油井钻架
The derrick.
…等我走到钻架那儿之后   你就可以介绍我的名字了
You'll see me walk up, and then you could say my name.
当你走上来之后…？
When you walk up?
是的，我会走上来，然后你就说…
Yes. You'll see me walk up, and then you could say,
“他是这片大山的爱子   照料着主的子民…”
"The proud son of these hills who tended his Father's flock,"
然后就可以说我的名字了
and then you could say my name.
那好吧
That's fine.
- 那之后呢？   - 之后我们就开始钻井
- And what happens then? - Well, then we start the drill.
丹尼尔，虽然祈福仪式很简单   但非常重要
It's a simple blessing, Daniel, but an important one.
就几句话，不会占用太长时间
It's just a few words. It won't take long.
- 什么时候开始？   - 你什么时候方便呢，伊莱？
- What time? - What time's good for you, Eli?
- 下午四点   - 那我们就定在四点开始
- 4:00. - Well, let's make it 4:00 then.
- 感谢你来拜访   - 谢谢您，我走了
- My thanks for your visit. - Good day. Thank you.
各位下午好
Afternoon, everyone.
跟我来
Come with me.
感谢你们每个人来此参加这项仪式
I thank you all so much for visiting with us at this time.
我已有幸拜访过你们中的某些家庭…
I've had the pleasure of meeting some of you
我也非常希望在今后几个月里
and I hope very much in the months to come,
能逐一拜访每户人家
I'll be able to visit with each and every one of you.
比起钻井找油来   我在演说方面的才能要差许多
I'm better at digging holes in the ground than making speeches,
所以就不发表长篇大论了
so let's forget the speech for this evening,
来一段简单的祈福吧
just make it a simple blessing.
众所周知，仅凭一个人无法采油
You see, one man doesn't prospect from the ground.
勘探需要发动群体的力量   在场各位就是合适的人选
It takes a whole community of good people, such as yourselves,
只有这样才好，大家住在一起
and this is good. We stay together.
一起祷告，一起工作
We pray together, we work together,
倘若有幸，上帝对我们的努力报以微笑…
and if the Good Lord smiles kindly on our endeavor,
我们还能一起分享天赐的财富
we share in the wealth together.
现在，在玛丽一号油井开钻之前…
Now, before we spud in Mary's Well Number One,
借了身边这位可爱小姐   玛丽·桑迪之芳名…
named for the lovely Miss Mary Sunday, here by my side,
她是这片大山的爱女
a proud daughter of these hills,
我想说的是: 愿主保佑我们的辛劳
I'd just like to say God bless these honest labors of ours, and, of course,
愿他也保佑在场的所有子民
God bless you all.
阿门
Amen.
现在去吧
Now go.
马上就好，请稍候
Won't be a minute.
H.W.，给我快点
Fast as you can, H.W.
准备好了没？
Are you ready to do this?
女士们先生们，我们开始了！
That's it, ladies and gentlemen!
感谢阿尔·罗斯的慷慨   大家可以享用些茶点…
Al Rose has very generously provided some refreshments for this occasion
茶点开销由他负责，谢谢你，阿尔
out of his own pocket. Thank you, Al.
请尽情享用美食，我马上回来
If you'll all just care to help yourselves, I'll be back in a minute.
玛丽
Mary.
玛丽·桑迪
Mary Sunday.
- 喜欢你的新裙子么？     - 很喜欢，谢谢您
- Do you like your new dress? - Yes. Thank you.
不客气，我想你会喜欢的
You're welcome. I thought you'd like it.
- 我来这儿你高兴么？     - 是的
- Are you happy I came here? - Yes.
你爸爸还打你么？他现在不打你了吧？
Your daddy doesn't hit you anymore, does he? Does he now?
最好他不打了，对么？
Better not, right?
我会照顾你的
I'll take care of you.
不让他再打你了，好不好？     不许再打了…现在你可以走了
No more hitting, right? No more hitting. Now go.
去玩吧，不用过来了
Go and play some more and don't come back.
丹尼尔
Daniel?
H.W，没什么事，快回去睡觉吧
lt's okay, H.W. Go back to sleep. Go on. Go back to sleep.
丹尼尔
Daniel.
丹尼尔！
Daniel!
怎么了？
What?
井下死了个人
Lost a man down the well.
- 谁？     - 乔伊·冈达
- What man? - Joe Gundha.
- 我认识他么？     - 不
- Did I know him? - No.
发生了什么事？
What happened?
往上抬
Pick it up.
设好闸
Set the brake.
- 绑好往下放     - 快绑好
- Tie it down. - Tie it on.
该死！
Shit!
我的天哪，尸体在哪儿？
God damn it. Where's the body?
- 正在打捞     - 好
- They're fishing it out now. - All right.
- 钻头呢？     - 在平台上
- Where's the bit? - It's on the deck.
把尸体弄干净，然后给他换套衣服
Clean him up. Put some clothes on him.
然后…
And...
再支一个帐篷
Set up a tent.
任何人下井之前，必须告知他人     听见没有？
Anyone goes down into the cellar, you tell somebody. Yes?
- 听见了，先生     - 知道了，先生
- Yes, sir. - Yes, sir.
先停工，到中午再说
Shut down till midday.
我还做了一个梦     是的，昨夜，我做了个梦
And I had a vision. Yes, last night, I had a vision
我感觉上帝的气息贯穿全身
and I felt God's breath move through me.
最后来到我的胃中
And it rolled down into my stomach.
气息在胃中翻滚
It sloshed around.
我的胃开始说话，不是呼喊，而是低语
And my stomach spoke in a whisper, not a shout,
- 用手触摸这名妇人，轻抚她的肌肤     - 是这样
"Touch this woman with your hands and caress her." Yes.
亲爱的亨特太太…
My dear Mrs. Hunter,
你患有关节炎，是不是？
you have arthritis, don't you?
- 是的，伊莱     - 是啊
- Yes, I do, Eli. - Yes.
有恶魔藏在你的手中     我要把这魔鬼吸出来
The devil is in your hands, and I will suck it out.
这回我不准备用热焰逼它出来
Now, I will not cast this ghost out with a fever
我内中的气息，教给我一种新的交流方式
for the new spirit inside me has shown me I have a new way to communicate.
用温柔的低语呼唤
It is a gentle whisper.
出来吧，魔鬼
Get out of here, ghost.
从里面出来吧
出来
Get out.
出来吧，魔鬼
Get out of here, ghost.
从里面出来吧
现在就离开这个女人，给我出来…
...and enter this woman's body now. - Get out of here, ghost.
出来后再也不要停留，永远离开
Get out of here. Don't you dare turn around and come back.
如果你敢回来
For if you do,
我会将愤怒的力量汇于脚尖     踢碎你的利齿
all the armies of my boot will kick you in the teeth
将你高高抛起，而后摔在泥中
and you will be cast up and thrown in the dirt
堕入地狱，永不超生！
and thrust back to perdition!
只要我有牙齿，就会来撕咬你
And as long as I have teeth, I will bite you,
如果没有牙齿，就用牙床嚼死你
and if I have no teeth, I will gum you!
只要我有双拳，就要来痛揍你！
And as long as I have fists, I will bash you!
快点给我离开，魔鬼！     快离开，魔鬼！
Now, get out of here, ghost! Get out of here, ghost!
快离开，魔鬼！
Get out of here, ghost!
它走了！
And it left!
- 哈利路亚!     - 哈利路亚!
- Hallelujah! - Hallelujah!
- 赞美主，赞美神圣日！     - 赞美主！
- Praise the Lord and his holy days! - Praise God!
- 阿门！谢谢各位     - 感谢耶稣，感谢主
- Amen! Thank you. - Thank you, Jesus. Thank you, God.
亲爱的亨特太太
My dear Mrs. Hunter.
跟我跳支舞吧
Dance with me.
- 感谢光临     - 真是一次美妙的布道
- Thanks for coming. - It was a wonderful sermon.
- 明天见？     - 明天见
- Will I see you tomorrow? - Yes.
伊莱
Eli.
油井昨晚发生了一场悲剧
Had a tragedy at the well last night.
是的，我听说了
Yes, I heard.
乔伊·冈达是个有虔诚信仰的人
Joe Gundha was a man of considerable faith.
他的葬礼在明天中午     你可以过来讲几句话
So if you wish to say a few words, his burial is at noon tomorrow.
丹尼尔，事故本来可以避免
Daniel, this accident could have been avoided.
在未蒙主恩的井下工作…
It is terrible to think of that well
- 实在太可怕了…     - 我的人12小时才换一班
- working away out there... - These men work in 12-hour shifts.
他们需要充分的休息
...unblessed. - They need their rest.
如果得不到充分休息     他们就会犯低级错误
If they don't have it, they start to make stupid mistakes.
我看见有人在工作时酗酒     难道你不应对此采取措施？
I've seen the men drinking. Don't you think that has something to do with this?
我的人需要充分休息     油井的生产才有保证
We need these men well-rested to bring in this well.
如果他们总来听你传道     就无法保证正常的休息
They can't get that if they're up here listening to your gospel,
那样的话，我们就没法产油     大家的钱也成了泡影
and then the well can't produce and blow gold all over the place.
我希望，当初要能多接触乔伊就好了
I wish I had more time with Joe Gundha.
也许我能帮他更多
More could have been done.
那样我们就没法产油     大家的钱也成了泡影
Then the well can't produce and blow gold all over the place.
你能否帮个忙，将他的私人财产…
Now, would you see to it that his personal possessions
转交给他的家人，好么？
find their way back to his family, please?
谢谢你
Thank you.
听说你正计划改建教堂
Heard you were planning some renovations.
是啊，聚会人数越来越多
Yes, our congregation is growing strongly.
- 我们需要更大的地方     - 你刚才那场跳神表演真是妙的很啊
- We need more room. - That was one goddamn hell of a show.
很荣幸有你相伴，丹尼尔
We were happy to have you, Daniel.
瓦斯，瓦斯！
Gas, gas, gas!
火源灭了！等在这儿     快灭了火源！
Lights out! Wait here. Wait here. Lights out!
快把那火掐了！
Put that fire out!
他受伤没有？H. W！     把他递给我！
Is he hurt? H.W.! Hand him down to me!
- 把他放下来！     - 接住
- Hand him down! - Here.
- 抓住没？     - 抓住了！
- Got him? - I've got him!
哦，老天
Oh, God.
坚持住
Come on.
把门打开
Open the door.
放开手吧，你没事了，你安全了
Let go. There you go. You're safe. You're safe.
你现在安全了，我把你带回来了     你安全了，把手放开吧，小子
You're safe now. I got you here. You're safe. Let go, son.
告诉我哪儿疼，告诉我哪儿疼     告诉我…
Tell me where it hurts. Tell me where it hurts. Tell me where...
- 你当时看见没有？     - 没有
- Did you see this? - No.
告诉我哪儿疼
Tell me where it hurts.
你哪里受伤了？你哪里受伤了？
Where does it hurt you? Where does it hurt you?
- 我听不见自己的声音     - 撞到脑袋了？
- I can't hear my voice. - Were you hit in the head?
是不是撞到脑袋了？告诉我！     如果是，就告诉我！
Were you hit in the head? Tell me! You have to tell me if you were!
我听不见自己的声音
I can't hear my voice.
我得去指挥把火扑灭，在这里等我
I have to go and deal with this now. You wait here for me.
明白没？你在这儿等我     我就回来，我马上回来
You understand? You wait here for me. I'll be back. I'll be back in a minute.
- 你等着     - 你别走！
- Wait here. - Don't leave!
我会照顾你的，呆着别动，我来搞定
I'm going to take care of you. Wait. Stay here, son. I'm going to fix this.
- 请你别走！     - 你会没事的
- Don't leave! - You're going to be fine!
在这儿等我
Wait for me here!
- 把他按住，按住他     - 不要走！
- Hold him down. Hold him down. - Don't leave!
得把绳缆割断，丹尼尔！
Got to break the cables, Daniel!
给我一把锤子！
Get me a hammer!
给你
Here you go.
后退！
Get back!
- 迈克尔     - 先生？
- Michael! - Sir!
带上戴夫，再叫两个人，去拿水管
Take Dave and two of the fellas, pick up some hoses...
比利，快去保护顶棚     温度太高就不好办了
Billy, protect the roof. Don't wait before it gets too hot.
干嘛那样愁眉不展？
What are you looking so miserable about?
我们脚下是油的海洋！
There's a whole ocean of oil under our feet!
它们只属于我，没有第二个主人！
No one can get at it except for me.
H.W.还好么？
H.W. okay?
不好
No, he isn't.
- 他在哪儿？     - 在食堂
- Where is he? - Mess room.
别哼哼了，够了，H.W. ，别哼哼了
That's enough now. That's enough, H.W. That's enough.
听见我说话么？能听见么？
Do you hear me? Can you hear me in there?
够了
That's enough.
- 抓住他的脚     - 抓住脚了
- Grab his legs. - I have his legs.
- 不，不     - 别这样，小伙子
- No. Nope. - No, lad.
把那个给我
Give me that.
稳住，就这样
Steady. That's it.
- 放松点孩子，放松     - 一会儿就好了
- Easy, boy. Easy. - Soon be over.
好，就这样，现在换另一边     把他翻过来
Yeah, and that's good. Now the other side. Turn him over.
马上就好
Almost done.
好了
That's it.
过来，结束了，都结束了
Come here. It's over. It's over.
我们在旧金山认识什么人么？
Who do we know in San Francisco
…或者洛杉矶，有谁可以帮忙的？
or Los Angeles, who could work with...
我们可以找个人，来当H.W.的老师
You know, we could... Someone, a teacher for H.W.
你来处理此事如何？
How could you figure out that?
打电话给…该死，那人叫什么来着？
Now, call... God damn it, what's his name?
旧金山的鲍勃·布罗迪？
Bob Brody in San Francisco?
打电话给鲍勃·布罗迪     让他找个老师过来
Call Bob Brody and get someone down here.
我马上去办
I'll do it right away.
我们什么时候能拿到钱，丹尼尔？
When do we get our money, Daniel?
你不是天命神医么？     你不是圣灵附体么？
Aren't you a healer? And a vessel for the Holy Spirit?
什么时候来把我儿子的耳朵治好？
When are you coming over and make my son hear again?
会不会啊你？
Can't you do that?
如果让我为油井祈福     这种事根本不会发生
lf you had let me bless the well, this wouldn't have happened.
- 丹尼尔…     - 你不该说这种话
- Daniel. - You shouldn't have done that.
你还欠第三启示教会五千美金…
You owe the Church of the Third Revelation $5,000
我们当初约定好的！ 你还欠第三启示教会五千美金…
as part of the arrangement that we made!
我们当初约定好的！
小矮人，想得美，门都没有！     让你尝尝泥浆浴的味道吧…
Don't even try it, you little runt! You splash around in here.
这样才对，这样好多了…
That's it, that's it.
我会把你就地活埋，伊莱
I'm going to bury you underground, Eli.
把你活埋了！
I'm going to bury you underground.
你太蠢了，埃布尔
You are a stupid man, Abel.
是你把生人请了进来     让他在我们头上撒野
You've let someone come in here and walk all over us.
是你让他进来，让他在此胡作非为
You let him in and do his work here,
你太蠢了，破坏了原先美好的一切
and you are a stupid man for what we could have had.
是上帝让我这么做的，伊莱     我已经尽力了
I followed His word, Eli. I tried.
你一直干坐着，根本没出力
You didn't do anything but sit down.
你不仅懒惰，而且愚蠢
You're lazy, and you're stupid.
你想用愚蠢来换取上帝的救赎？
Do you think God is going to save you for being stupid?
主不会救赎愚蠢的灵魂，埃布尔
He doesn't save stupid people, Abel.
就你做的这点破事，真想把你捏死     大蠢蛋！
I will tear you apart for what you've done, you stupid man!
他怎么来的？你知不知道？     我知道！
How did he come here? Do you really know? I know!
- 儿子，你别…不要…     - 不许吵！
- Son, don't do this, please! - Be quiet!
闭上你的嘴，埃布尔！     是你那个蠢儿子干的
Shut your mouth, Abel! lt was your stupid son!
是保罗让那家伙过来的，我知道
lt was Paul who told him to come here. I know it.
他跟那家伙说
He went to him and he said,
“我那愚蠢软弱的爸爸会让出土地的…
"My stupid, weak father will give away his lots.
快去搞定他吧”…     你果然就被人家轻松搞定了
"Go and take him." And you let it happen.
真是老鼠的儿子会打洞啊
A stupid father to a stupid son.
出来吧
Get out of there!
有什么事么？
Can I help you?
丹尼尔？
Daniel?
- 你是哪位？     - 我叫亨利
- Who's that? - My name is Henry.
什么？
Yeah?
我叫亨利
I'm Henry.
能为您做什么嘛？
What can I do for you?
我是亨利·普莱维，来自丰迪拉克郡     (位于美国威斯康辛州)
I'm Henry Plainview. I'm from Fond du Lac.
我是你的兄弟，我们同父异母
I'm your brother, from another mother.
我父亲是欧内斯特
Ernest is my father.
你是谁？
Who are you?
亨利
Henry.
- 玛丽·布兰兹是你的母亲？     - 是的，先生，正是
- Mary Branch? Is that your mother? - Yes, sir, that's right.
从报上听说了你的油井，还有你的成就
I read about your gusher in the paper, about your success.
听说我发家了，你就来找我了？
You heard about my strike? You just show up?
我们的父亲过世了
Our father's dead.
我听说欧内斯特死了，就想来找你
Ernest died, I heard. I wanted to find you.
什么时候死的？
When?
三个月前，安娜贝尔寄给我一封信
Three months ago. I got a letter from Annabelle.
我的姐姐安娜贝尔？
My sister, Annabelle?
- 她现在在哪儿？     - 还在老家，丰迪拉克郡
- Where is she? - Still at home. Fond du Lac.
你大老远从威斯康辛过来     就为了告诉我这个？
You came all the way from Wisconsin to tell me this?
我从新墨西哥州过来的     我在那儿待了一段时间
I'm coming from New Mexico. I've been there.
就为了过来找你
I came to find you.
你知道有我这个兄弟么？
Did you know about me?
你有证件么？
Do you have identification?
那封信你带了没？
Do you have this letter?
- 你从哪儿来？     - 新墨西哥州
- Where are you coming from? - From New Mexico.
我知道，在哪个城市呢？
Yes, I know, but from where?
在银城，我在那儿待了两年
Silver City. I've been there for two years.
多年来我一直想成立自己的钻探队
I was trying drilling of my own for years.
- 在德克萨斯和路易斯安那租地探油     - 找到油了么？
- Getting leases in Texas. Louisiana. - Anything that produced?
没有，比起你的成功，我毫无所获
No. Not like your success, no.
- 结婚了么？     - 没有
- Are you married? - No.
我曾坐过大牢，那日子真难熬
I spent time in jail. I had a stretch of very bad time.
身无分文，在路易斯安那被人抓了
I had nothing. I was picked up in Louisiana.
身上拴着铁链，做了半年修路苦力
I worked on a chain gang for six months building roads.
真是不堪回首啊
That was a very hard time.
你结婚了没有？
Are you married?
你为了什么坐牢的？
What were you in jail for?
说真的，虽然我也干过不少坏事
Believe it or not, for all the terrible things I've gotten myself into,
但那次被抓的时候     我什么坏事也没干
when they picked me up, I hadn't done anything.
但我也是罪有应得……
But I've done my share of things
具体的罪恶么，恕我不能明述了
that shouldn't be talked about.
喝了它…喝了它！
Drink it. Drink it!
来吧
Come on.
那么…
So...
你想要什么，亨利？
What do you want, Henry?
什么也不要
Nothing.
如果不吝，我愿意为你打工
If you can spare something, I can work for you in any way.
不久后我可能还得继续漂泊     最后回老家丰迪拉克
I know I'll keep moving, before long, to get back to Fond du Lac.
- 你有积蓄么？     - 有一点
- Do you have any money? - Some.
- 但不多     - 跟我说实话
- Not much. - Just answer me directly.
你刚才还说“什么也不要”     然后又说想留下干活
You say "nothing," then you say you'd like to stay and work.
如果你只说想留下干活     我听了会更舒服
And it's better, I'd just like to hear you say you'd like to be here.
我想留下
I'd like to be here.
我干活很卖力的     我在钻油平台上干过，也修过铁路
I'm a good worker. I worked cable tool rigs, built railroads.
不需要你多加关照的
I won't need any favors.
好
Good.
我妈妈知道这事么？
What did my mother know?
我不知道
I don't know.
也许她知道，但故意回避此事     装作不知，是否如此我不清楚
I don't know if she knew and looked the other way, if she never knew.
你为何离开家？
Why did you leave?
我只知道你和父亲不合
I know you didn't get on with our father.
我曾为地质勘探队工作过     并随他们一起去了堪萨斯…
I worked for Geological Survey and went to Kansas.
我没法留在家里，觉得没法呆
I couldn't stay there. I just couldn't.
我不喜欢给自己找理由
I don't like to explain myself.
- 亨利，你容易动怒吗？     - 为了什么？
- Are you an angry man, Henry? - About what?
那你会嫉妒嘛？容易心生嫉妒嘛？
Are you envious? Do you get envious?
我想没有…没有吧
I don't think so, no.
我的内心总在斗争
I have a competition in me.
我不愿意见到其他人成功
I want no one else to succeed.
- 对大部分人，我都怀有恨意     - 我心中已经没有那些东西了
- I hate most people. - That part of me is gone.
投入工作的热情，遭受挫折的懊恼
Working and not succeeding,
那些失败的往昔都已离我远去…
all my failures have left me...
我已经不在乎了
I just don't care.
在我心里的东西，在你心里也应该有
Well, if it's in me, it's in you.
有很多次，我看着别人     找不到半点中意的地方
There are times when I look at people and I see nothing worth liking.
我想挣足够多的钞票，多到足以     远离俗世的烦扰，一个人自己过
I want to earn enough money I can get away from everyone.
你儿子怎么办？
What will you do about your boy?
我不知道
I don't know.
事情会发生变化也说不定
Maybe it'll change.
昨日是否会重回你身边？我不知道     也许没有人知道
Does your sound come back to you? I don't know. Maybe no one knows that.
- 连医生也不知道     - 孩子他妈呢？
- Doctor might not know that. - Where's his mother?
我不想谈论这事…
I don't want to talk about those things.
我能看到人性最丑陋的那一面
I see the worst in people, Henry.
负面印象太多，甚至无需刻意回想
I don't need to look past seeing them to get all I need.
经过长年日积月累     我的恨意越蓄越深
I've built up my hatreds over the years, little by little.
你来之后，在我的生活中     又打开了一扇崭新的窗
Having you here gives me a second breath of life.
我不能再独自一个人战斗了
I can't keep doing this on my own
和这些人…抗争
with these people.
丹尼尔，丹尼尔，快醒醒！ 丹尼尔！
Daniel! Daniel, wake up! Daniel!
我得去和列车长说几句话
Just have to go and have a word with the conductor.
很快就回来
I'll be right back.
你呆着…懂了么？待在这儿别动
You stay here. You understand? You stay here.
我马上回来
I'll be right back.
不！不~！
No! No!
不！！
No!
- 特尔福德！     - 普莱维
- Tilford! - Plainview.
我兄弟亨利·普莱维，来自丰迪拉克
This is my brother, Henry Plainview from Fond du Lac.
H.M. 特尔福德，很高兴认识你
H.M. Tilford. Pleasure.
- 亨利·普莱维     - J.J.卡特
Henry Plainview. J.J. Carter.
那么…
So...
- 我们开始？     - 好吧
- Shall we? - Yes.
你儿子情况如何？
How's your boy?
- 谢谢关心     - 有什么要我们帮忙么？
- Thank you for asking. - Is there anything we can do?
有你的关心就足够了
Thanks for asking is enough.
那么，你打算怎么办？
So what are your plans?
你是在问我这里的地怎么卖？
Is this about buying up my tracts here?
是的
Yes.
电报里提的是我在野狼山的租约
The cable was about my Coyote Hills lease.
- 那份租约我们也想买     - 野狼山那份，你们开价多少？
- We'd like that, too. - What's your offer on Coyote Hills?
- 十五万美金，转让所有权利     - 没问题…接下来呢？
- We'll offer 150,000 for full title. - That's a deal. What's next?
你在小波士顿有11000英亩地     有一口出油井…
You have 11,000 acres in Little Boston. You have one proven well
- 但已受损…     - 有三口出油井
- that was damaged... - I have three wells proven.
看来你们调查不够，出油井一共三口
You haven't been paying attention. That's three proven wells.
你现在只需坐等收钱
We'll make you a millionaire while you're sitting here
我们可以让你马上变成百万富翁
from one minute to the next.
卖了地之后我还能干嘛？
And what else would I do with myself?
- 你在问我？     - 我以后还能干嘛？
- Are you asking me? - What else would I do with myself?
照顾你儿子
Take care of your son.
我又不了解你想干嘛
I don't know what you would do.
如果此刻你是我     标准石油的人想来买你的地…
If you were me and Standard offered to buy what you had
还出价一百万美金，就会想问原因     为什么你们要这么做？
for a million dollars, why? So, why?
你知道原因
You know why.
我建议你们学学其他人     凭自己的力量去挖去找
Yeah, you fellas should just scratch around in the dirt
而不是直接用钱去换别人辛勤的果实
and find it like the rest of us, instead of buying up someone else's hard work.
年轻人，我自己也挖过找过
I've scratched around the dirt, son.
你们是不是准备上调运价啊？
You going to change your shipping costs?
我们才不会操纵运价呢     这都是铁路公司的决定…
We don't dictate shipping costs. That's railroad business.
铁路公司不是你们的产业？
You don't own the railroads?
你们当然会啦，这点毫无疑问
'Course you do. Of course you do.
你准备把这些油送到哪儿去？
Where you going to put it all?
到哪儿？
Where?
如果想造一条管线，然后和     联合石油做买卖，那就请便…
Build a pipeline? Make a deal with Union Oil? Be my guest.
但如果你的计划没能实现…
But if you can't pull it off,
到时候守着偌大一片油田     却无处可去，岂不是很惨
you've got an ocean of oil under your feet with nowhere to go.
为什么不交给我们？     我们会让你发大财
Why not turn it over to us? We'll make you rich.
你可以腾出时间来照顾孩子
You spend time with your boy.
这儿的油田是一个惊人的发现
It's a great discovery.
现在让我们来协助你吧
Now, let us help you.
你竟然教训我该怎么带孩子…
Did you just tell me how to run my family?
你的地现在能卖个好价钱     这一点也许更为重要
lt might be more important now that you've proven the field
我们也愿出大钱买下你的地
and we're offering to buy you out.
总有一天，我会进你的屋子
One night I'm going to come to you, inside of your house,
或是趁你熟睡的时候     用刀把你的喉咙割断
or wherever you're sleeping, and I'm going to cut your throat.
什么？
What?
你在说些什么啊？你是不是疯了？
What are you talking about? Have you gone crazy?
- 你没听明白我说的？     - 我全听见了
- Did you hear what I said? - I heard what you said,
- 你要干嘛？     - 不许教训我该怎样抚养儿子
- why did you say it? - You don't tell me about my son.
你发什么疯，竟然威胁要割我喉咙？
Why are you acting insane and threatening to cut my throat?
- 不许教训我该怎样抚养儿子     - 我根本没教训你！
- You don't tell me about my son. - I'm not telling you anything!
请你理智一点     如果刚才我有所冒犯，我道歉
I'm asking you to be reasonable. If I've offended you, I apologize.
那你就等着瞧好吧
You'll see what I can do.
这三千英亩是B.L. 哈珀的农场
This parcel here is the 3,000-acre ranch owned by B.L. Harper.
这是圣路易欧比斯珀郡的郡属土地
This is San Luis Obispo County land.
还有从这儿直到海岸     都被联合石油收购了
And from here to the coast, it's all Union Oil.
这儿呢？为什么我没买下这里？
What's this? Why don't I own this?
- 为什么我没买？     - 这是班迪的地产
- Why don't I own this? - That's the Bandy tract.
就是那个在我们收购土地的时候     拒不合作的老头
He was the holdout, when we were doing the buying.
他想先和你谈谈
He had hoped to speak with you.
你的管线不能绕过他的地盘么？
Can't you just build the pipeline around this tract?
我要有这个能耐，就能把蒂哈查皮山     (加州南部横向山脉)再加长50英里了
Can I build around 50 miles of Tehachapi mountains?
别在我面前说蠢话，阿尔
Don't be thick in front of me, Al.
- 我可以再去问他     - 不用，我亲自去和他说
- I can go to him again. - No, I'll go and talk to the man.
我去说，你们学着点
I'll talk to him. Show you how it's done.
就到这儿，亨利，你收拾一下
All right. Pack it up, Henry.
- 我儿子的房间多大？     - 他和另一个孩子合住
- How big is his room? - He's sharing with another boy.
- 和谁？     - 一个比他大的孩子，12岁左右
- Who? - An older boy. About 12.
名叫巴拉德，在那儿已经住了一年
He's been there for a year. Named Ballard.
- 他的房间有多大？     - 不大不小，够两个人住的
- How big is the room? - It's a fair size. Got enough space.
你要带亨利去见联合石油的人？
Are you taking Henry with you to meet Union Oil?
- 你是威廉·班迪的儿子？     - 他的孙子
- Are you the son of William Bandy? - Grandson.
- 他在么？     - 不，他出去了
- Is he here? - No, he's out.
他去哪儿了？
Where is he?
都说了他出去了，你有什么事？
Told you, he's out. Now, what do you want?
我是丹尼尔·普莱维     想和你爷爷谈谈他地产的事情
I'm Daniel Plainview. I want to talk with him about his property.
- 要谈些什么？     - 我还是和他亲自谈比较好
- About what? - I believe I'll talk with him about that.
- 你是个油矿主，对不对？     - 是的
- You're that oilman, aren't you? - That's right.
我们不要你来挖油
We don't want you drilling out here.
我也不想来啊…他什么时候回来？
I don't want it either. Now, when will he be back?
几天以后吧
Few days.
跟他说，我想找他谈谈     不是挖油的事
Tell him I'd like to speak with him. Not about drilling.
我一周后再来
And I'll be back in a week.
把这根留在玻璃陈列柜里
Put that in a glass case.
这杯酒敬给联合石油…
Here's to Union Oil.
还有数百英里的输油管线…
Hundred miles of pipeline,
以及本州所有的独立油矿主
and all the independent producers of this great state.
干杯
Cheers.
在丰迪拉克老家有幢房子
There's that house in Fond du Lac
是约翰·霍利斯特造的     你记得那房子么？
that John Hollister built. Do you remember it?
小时候我觉得     那是我所见过的最漂亮的房子
I thought as a boy that was the most beautiful house I'd ever seen,
梦想能拥有她
and I wanted it.
我想住在那房子里
I wanted to live in it.
在里面吃饭…
And eat in it.
在里面打扫
And clean it.
打小我就想生很多孩子     让他们在房外奔跑戏耍
And even as a boy, I wanted to have children to run around in it.
现在的你能把任何梦想变成现实
You can have anything you'd like now, Daniel.
你应该去实现自己的梦想
And you should.
- 你准备在哪儿建房子？   - 也许就建在这儿，在海边
- Where are you going to build it? - Here, maybe. Near the ocean.
按照那幢房子的样式建？
Would you make it look like that house?
现在如果再见到那幢房子   我也许会嗤之以鼻的
I think if I saw that house now, it'd make me sick.
我们去大吃一顿吧，再找些女人乐乐
We can eat and get some women.
就带她们去桃树舞厅…
Take them to the Peachtree dance.
我说，先把自己灌个半醉   再带女人去桃树舞厅如何
I say get liquored up and take them to the Peachtree dance.
好啊
Yeah.
拜托，给我点钱吧
Can I have some money, please?
给我点钱好吗
我想问你几件事
I want you to tell me something.
问什么？
What?
希尔家旁边的农场叫什么名字？
What's the name of the farm next to the Hill House?
What was the name of the farm next to the Hill House?
- 我记不起来了…   - 你是谁？
- I can't remember... - Who are you?
我会走的，丹尼尔
I'll leave, Daniel.
你到底是谁？
Who are you?
我谁都不是
I'm no one.
让我起身吧，我马上消失
Just let me get up and go.
我有兄弟么？
Do I have a brother?
我在国王城遇见一个人   他说他是你的兄弟
I met a man in King City who said he was your brother.
我们做了几个月的朋友
We were friends for months.
在国王城一起共事
Working in King City.
他想来这儿找你，丹尼尔
And he wanted to make his way to you, Daniel.
但当时我们没有钱
We didn't have any money.
后来他得肺结核死了
He died of tuberculosis.
不是死于暴力…
He wasn't harmed.
也不是被杀的，就是正常的那种死亡
Wasn't killed, nothing bad.
但他跟我提起过你
But he told me about you,
于是我借用了他的身份
and I just took his story,
拿了他的日记
used his diary.
丹尼尔
Daniel.
丹尼尔，我是你的朋友
Daniel, I'm your friend.
我不想伤害你
I'm not trying to hurt you.
从来没想过…
Never.
只想找口饭吃
Just survive.
不！
No!
哪位？
Who is it?
我叫班迪
I'm Bandy.
是你，你是…
Yes. Yes.
威廉·班迪
William Bandy.
我想租你的地
Yeah, I'd like to lease your land.
我曾邀请你去我那儿谈…
I had asked for you to come and talk to me before.
可你在忙着租地，没来找我
When you were leasing land.
说的没错
That's right, yes.
你知道，我儿子病得厉害，我抽不开身
My boy's been very sick, you know.
那是在你儿子生病之前的事
This was before your boy got sick.
我听说你想修一条管线
Now, I know that you would like to build a pipeline
而且要经过我的土地
through my property.
- 我听得没错吧？   - 完全正确
- Is that right, what I've heard? - It's absolutely right. And,
那好…
well...
只是一根八英寸粗的管子，如果你点头   我们可以把它埋在地下……
Eight inch pipe. It could be buried with your consent.
我保证，绝不会给您带来任何影响
I guarantee you absolutely no disruption...
上帝…
God.
上帝把你要做的事告诉了我
God has told me what you must do.
我要做的事？
And what is that?
你得在耶稣基督的圣血中受洗
You should be washed in the blood of Jesus Christ.
但我已经做了
But I am.
我已经受洗了，班迪先生   我早就受洗了
I have been washed, Mr. Bandy. I have been.
这是你唯一的救赎之道   是你得偿所愿的唯一方法
It's your only way to salvation. And your only way for what you want.
来第三启示教堂吧
You can take it at the Church of the Third Revelation.
我可以付你三千美元
I'll pay you $3,000.
我希望你加入我们的教会
I'd like you to be part of our church.
我付你五千美元
I'll pay you $5,000.
快来受洗吧
Be baptized.
请求主宽恕你的罪
Be forgiven for the sin that you've done.
你说的罪恶…是指什么，班迪先生？
What sin are you referring to, Mr. Bandy?
因为我在这里钻井？
My sin of drilling?
我真心希望每个人都能得到救赎   大家说是不是？
I truly wish everyone could be saved, don't you?
是的
Yes.
只可惜事实并非如我们所愿
I am afraid that's just not the case.
号称所有人都能得救，那是谎言   大家说是不是？
The doctrine of universal salvation is a lie, is it not?
- 是骗人的   - 是骗人的
- It's a lie. - It's a lie.
我希望每个人都能得救，但这不可能！   不可能人人都得救！
I wish everyone could be saved, but they won't. No, they won't.
要想得救，你只有…
You will never be saved if you...
接受圣血的洗礼！
Reject the blood.
好
Good.
这儿有寻求救赎的罪人么？
Now, is there a sinner here looking for salvation?
我指新来的人
A new member?
我再问一遍：
I'll ask it again.
这儿有寻求主赦的罪人么？
Is there a sinner here looking for God?
有
Yes.
让我来
Allow me.
谢谢你的光临，丹尼尔兄弟
Thank you for coming, brother Daniel.
谢谢你，伊莱
Thank you, Eli.
我们这儿有位希望得到救赎的罪人
We have a sinner with us here who wishes for salvation!
- 丹尼尔，你是罪人么   - 是的
- Daniel, are you a sinner? - Yes.
主听不见你的话，丹尼尔
The Lord can't hear you, Daniel.
大声说给主听，说响点，没关系的
Say it to him. Go ahead and speak to him. It's all right.
- 好的   - 跪对上帝
- Yes. - Down on your knees.
向他祈祷
Pray to him.
抬头向上苍，说出你的罪过
Look up to the sky and say it.
你想让我说什么？
What do you want me to say?
丹尼尔，你为这里带来了利益和财富
Daniel, you've come here and you've brought good and wealth,
但也带来了恶习，你是个堕落者
but you have also brought your bad habits as a backslider.
你追逐着身边的美色   却舍弃了自己的孩子
You've lusted after women, and you have abandoned your child.
你舍弃了亲手养大的孩子
Your child, that you raised, you have abandoned
只因为他有病，因为你有罪
all because he was sick and you have sinned.
现在跟我说:“ 我是一个罪人”
So say it now. I am a sinner.
- 我是一个罪人   - 大声说
- I am a sinner. - Say it louder.
- 我是一个罪人   - 我是一个罪人
- I am a sinner. - I am a sinner.
再大声点，丹尼尔！我是一个罪人！
Louder, Daniel! I am a sinner!
- 我是一个罪人！   - 主啊，我错了！
- I am a sinner. - I am sorry, Lord.
- 主啊，我错了！   - 请赐我圣血吧！
- I am sorry, Lord. - I want the blood.
- 请赐我圣血吧！   - 你舍弃了自己的孩子
- I want the blood. - You have abandoned your child.
我舍弃了自己的孩子
I have abandoned my child.
- 我绝不再甘堕落   - 我绝不再甘堕落
- I will never backslide. - I will never backslide.
我曾迷失，现又重归本我
I was lost, but now I am found.
- 我曾迷失，现又重归本我   - 我舍弃了自己的孩子
- I was lost, but now I'm found. - I have abandoned my child.
跟我说，快说
Say it. Say it.
- 我舍弃了自己的孩子   - 大声点，说大声点！
- I abandoned my child. - Say it louder. Say it louder!
我舍弃了自己的孩子！
I've abandoned my child!
我丢下自己的亲儿子不管！
I've abandoned my boy!
乞求圣血吧
Now beg for the blood!
快给我圣血，伊莱，让我离开这儿
Just give me the blood, Eli. Let me get out of here.
主啊，请赐我圣血   驱走我体内的恶魔！
Give me the blood, Lord, and let me get away!
你是否愿接受耶稣基督做你的主   认他做你的救赎者？
Do you accept Jesus Christ as your Lord and Savior?
- 是的，我愿意   - 快出来吧，恶魔！
- Yes, I do. - Get out of here, devil!
出来吧恶魔！出来吧罪恶！
Out, devil! Out, sin!
- 让我感受主的力量吧，伊莱   - 你是否愿接受…
- Let me feel the power of the Lord, Eli. - Do you accept
第三启示教会成为你灵魂的引路人？
the Church of the Third Revelation as your spiritual guide?
- 快给我出来！   - 你的主在哪儿，伊莱？
- Get out of here, ghost! - Where is your Lord, Eli?
- 给我出来，滚回你的老窝去！   - 他在哪儿？他在那儿！
- Get out! Go back where you belong! - Where is he? There he is!
你愿接受耶稣基督为救世主么？
Do you accept Jesus Christ as your Savior?
我愿意
Yes, I do.
“ 你肩上的罪是否卸空
Would you be free from the burden of sin?
“ 神力蕴于圣血中
There's power in the blood
Power in the blood
“ 你是否击败过恶魔，赢得光荣
Would you o'er evil a victory win?
管线到手了
There's a pipeline.
“ 血中的神力无比尊崇
There's wonderful power in the blood
“神力啊，神力，伟大的神力
There is power, power wonder-working power
存于耶稣宝血之中…”
In the blood of the Lamb
赞美主！
Praise the Lord!
欢迎入教，普莱维兄弟
Welcome to the fold, brother Plainview.
欢迎你，普莱维兄弟，愿主保佑你
Welcome, brother Daniel. God bless you.
愿主保佑你
God bless you.
- 哈利路亚   - 阿门
- Hallelujah. - Amen.
欢迎回家，兄弟
Welcome home, brother.
好了……到此为止吧
That's enough. That's enough, now.
他得自己将圣灵引入体内
He must take the spirit in on his own.
我们又多了一位新的兄弟
We have a new member.
- 是的，兄弟   - 哈利路亚
- Yes, brother. - Hallelujah.
- 哈利路亚   - 阿门
- Hallelujah. - Amen.
- 普莱维先生非常慷慨   - 亲爱的玛丽…
- My sweet Mary. - Mr. Plainview has been generous
他愿捐出五千美金
enough to make a $5,000 donation
捐给教会，虽然这笔钱还没到帐
to the church which we are still waiting for.
这感觉真好，这感觉真好
That does me good. That does me good.
欢迎回家，儿子
Welcome home, son.
这位是乔治·雷诺兹，聋校的老师
This here's George Reynolds. Teacher from the deaf school.
- 普莱维先生   - 弗莱彻
- Mr. Plainview. - Fletcher.
你都变得这么重了
You're too heavy for me.
想吃点东西么？
Do you want to get something to eat?
看见没，那边就是输油管线   一直通到大海
That's the pipeline, see? All the way to the sea.
过来
Come here.
我爱你，儿子
I love you, son.
让我好好看看你
Let's take a look at you.
好了，够了，够了…
All right. That's it, that's it. That's it.
让我们弄点好吃的吧
Let's get some decent food inside of you.
我们到这儿来，就是来   吃一顿丰盛高档的大餐
That's all we need here is a good, strong, expensive meal.
你饿了么？
You hungry?
- 服务生？   - 您好，先生
- Waiter? - Yes, sir.
两份牛排，一杯威士忌   给这位年轻人来一杯水
Two steaks, a whiskey, and water for him.
- 再来一杯羊奶   - 好的，先生
- And goat's milk. - Very good, sir.
我们请了位老师来帮你
We're going to have this teacher help you.
他会照顾好我们大家的，听明白了？
He's going to help take care of all of this. Understand?
我需要你，需要你的帮助
'Cause I need you. Need your help.
现在我们的公司已一切就绪   过来…
Got everything we need now to build this company. Come here.
下午好
Good afternoon.
- 你好么？   - 很高兴再次见到你
- How are you doing? - It's nice to see you again.
- 我们需要四个人的桌子   - 我马上派人安排
- We need four. - I'll have them right up.
- 下午好，丹尼尔   - 哦，特尔福德
- Good afternoon, Daniel. - Tilford.
下午好
Good afternoon.
- 你好，我是H.M.特尔福德！   - 用不着那么大声
- Hello! H.M. Tilford! - You don't have to shout.
很高兴见到你们
Pleasure.
小波士顿这儿不错
It's good to be in Little B.
- 这里应该下点雨   - 是啊，没错
- Could use some rain out here. - Yeah, we could.
- 我们的饮料来了   - R.J.，伦敦烤肉味道如何？
- There we go. - R.J., how's the London broil?
我们比这些人先要的饮料
Believe we ordered these drinks before those people.
- R.J.，说说看，这儿的烤肉如何？   - 对不起，先生们，我很抱歉
- R.J., tell us. How's the London broil? - Excuse me, gentlemen. Sorry.
先生，我很抱歉   你们的牛排马上就来
I am sorry about that, sir. I'll have your steaks right out.
- 听说海龟汤很不错   - 是么？
- So that green turtle soup is fantastic. - Is it?
非常美味
lt's delicious.
听上去合我胃口
Sounds good to me.
标准石油愿出一百万美元   收购我在小波士顿的租地
So Standard offered us a million dollars for the Little Boston leases.
我告诉特尔福德，让他一边去
I told H.M. Tilford where he could shove that.
于是我找了联合石油做生意！   还修了一条管线！
And we made a deal with Union! On the pipeline!
把脚下的这片油海慢慢运出去
And that whole ocean of oil underneath our fields.
- 15万美金   - 好
...$150,000. - Yes.
我们需要钱开井
We needed the money to drill.
- 那人是谁？   - 我去和他说
- Who is this guy? - I go out to meet him.
他的地里有油，我们想买下所有权
He's getting oil on the property. We're trying to make a claim on it.
然后给他一百万报价
Offered him a million dollars.
- 他却一口回绝   - 好了，我饿了
- Turned us down flat. - Well, I'm hungry.
桔子馅饼，土豆泥，还有青豆…
Orange fritters, mashed potatoes, green peas.
- 都是这种东西？   - 好罢
- All the way around? - All right.
等一等
Hold on.
请你往那边看
I want you to look over there.
- 丹尼尔，我来介绍一下…   - 往那边看，看见没？
- Daniel, let me introduce... - Look over there. You see?
那是我儿子，你看见他了么？
That's my son. See him?
- 我看见了   - 你看见了？
- Yes. - Do you see?
我看见他了
I see him.
别教训我该怎么抚养后代
You don't tell me how to raise my family.
我警告你，别教训我该怎么抚养后代
I told you not to tell me how to raise my family.
丹尼尔…
Daniel...
你现在看见什么了？
So what do you see?
- 我很高兴你的生意能…   - 是的，我和联合石油的生意成了
- I'm very happy for you that the deal... - Yes, I made a deal with Union.
- 我的儿子也很快乐，很安全   - 恭喜你
- My son is happy. He's safe. - Congratulations.
- 现在由我照顾他，所以…   - 那样很好
- I'm taking care of him now, so... - Excellent.
你看上去就像个傻瓜   是不是啊，特尔福德？
You look like a fool, don't you, Tilford?
- 是的   - 是的
- Yes. - Yes.
说“是”就对了
Yes, you do.
请见谅，先生们
Excuse me, gentlemen.
请原谅我，先生们   也请原谅他
Excuse me, gentlemen. Excuse him, gentlemen.
我早告诉你我会这么做了
I told you what I was going to do.
我的儿子…
My son.
桑迪先生，听说你要离开我们教区
Mr. Sunday, I understand that you're leaving our fair community.
- 是的，我打算出去传道   - 你要去哪儿？
- Yes, I'm going on a mission. - Where you going?
去石油谷和塔夫脱   然后到贝克斯菲尔德
Oildale, Taft, and then on to Bakersfield.
那么，我想说…
Well, I want you to know...
三刻钟时间
Three quarters of an hour.
你为我们做了很多
...you done a great job for us.
- 谢谢，我在祈祷时会祝福你的   - 非常感谢你
- Thank you. You will be in my prayers. - I thank you very much.
联合石油公司，加州圣保拉市
Union Oil Company, Santa Paula, California.
“妇人说，先生，请把这水赐给我
"The woman saith unto him, 'Sir, give me this water
1927年   “妇人说，先生，请把这水赐给我
1927年
"'and I shall thirst not, neither come hither to draw."'
叫我不渴，也不用来这么远打水”   1927年
叫我不渴，也不用来这么远打水”
进来，进来吧
Come in, come in.
我们能单独谈谈么？
Can we be alone?
这是我最亲密的伙伴，我对他没有秘密
This is my closest associate. He hears everything.
- 我还是想和你私下交谈   - 你又张不了嘴
- I'd prefer to speak to you in private. - You can't speak.
那就用你的手比划吧
So why don't you flap your hands about
让那谁谁代你说   这些日子你都去哪儿了
and have what's-his-name tell me where you've been.
你以为我不知道你小子去了哪儿？
Or do you think I don't know?
关于此事我很难开口…
This is hard for me to say.
先要说的是，我非常非常爱你
I'll tell you first, I love you very much.
从你身上，我学会了热爱事业
I've learned to love what I do because of you.
我准备离开这里
I'm leaving here.
我要去墨西哥
I'm going to Mexico.
我还会带上玛丽，去墨西哥
I'm taking Mary, and I'm going to Mexico.
我很想念在外工作的生活
I miss working outside.
也很想念油田
I miss the fields.
可能过不多久
It'll only be for a time,
我会成立自己的钻探队
for me to do my own drilling
然后开创自己的公司
and start my own company.
是时候改变一下了
It's time to make a change.
这样一来，你我就变成对手了
This makes you my competitor.
- 不不，我没有那个意思…   - 你就是这个意思，孩子
- No. No, it's not like that. - It is like that, boy.
你自己的公司？不错嘛！
Your own company, huh?
是的
That's right.
在墨西哥？
In Mexico?
是的
Yes.
犯什么浑啊你！到底想干嘛？
You are making such a misstep. So, what are you doing?
我知道我们有很多事意见不一致
I know you and I have disagreed over many things.
我宁愿当你是父亲，而不是合作伙伴
I'd rather keep you as my father than my partner.
那就说出来！
Then say it.
如果你有话要说，我希望你自己开口…
If you've got something to say to me, then say it.
我想听你说，不想你身后的那条狗叫
I'd like to hear you speak instead of your little dog.
我要和妻子一起去墨西哥
I'm going to Mexico with my wife.
我要离开你
I'm going away from you.
看来这不难，是不是？
That wasn't so hard, was it?
你所做的会毁了我们两个
Killing us with what you're doing.
你正在扼杀我心目中的好儿子形象
You're killing my image of you as my son.
你太固执了，听不进别人的建议
You are stubborn. You won't listen.
你不是我的儿子
You're not my son.
请别那样说，我知道你是随口说说
Please don't say that. I know you don't mean it.
这是事实，你不是我的儿子   从来都不是
It's the truth. You're not my son. You never have been.
你是一个孤儿
You're an orphan!
听说过这个词么？
Did you ever hear that word?
把我的话告诉他
Tell him what I said.
你今天所作的，和你的身份蛮配
You operated here today like one.
我早该想到有这一天
I should have seen this coming.
我早该知道，经过了这么多年…
I should have known that, under this all, these past years
你对我的怨气一点点积累   最后变成了新的仇恨
you've been building new hate for me, piece by piece.
我甚至都不知道你是谁   你身上根本没我的影子
I don't even know who you are because you have none of me in you.
你是别人的孩子
You're someone else's.
你的愤怒，你的怨意
This anger. Your maliciousness.
还有你对我的消极态度…
Backwards dealings with me.
你是装在篮子里的孤儿   是我从沙漠中捡来的…
You're an orphan from a basket in the middle of the desert.
收养你不为别的，只为买地时   身边有张俏脸蛋，诓人容易些
And I took you for no other reason than I needed a sweet face to buy land.
你听见没有？
Did you get that?
现在你总算知道真相了
So now you know.
看着我！你比烂货更下贱
Look at me! You're lower than a bastard.
在你体内根本没有我的血   你不过是篮子里装的小烂货
You have none of me in you. You're just a bastard from a basket.
感谢主，我体内没有你的血
I thank God I have none of you in me.
你不是我儿子   只是个不起眼的对手
Not my son. Just a little piece of competition.
篮子里的烂货
Bastard from a basket.
篮子里的烂货！
Bastard from a basket!
你是篮子里的烂货！
You're a bastard from a basket!
起来，丹尼尔先生
Get up, Mr. Daniel.
丹尼尔先生
Mr. Daniel.
丹尼尔先生，有人来拜访
Mr. Daniel, you've got a visitor.
醒醒，丹尼尔先生
Wake up, Mr. Daniel.
先生？
Sir?
你可以走了
You can leave us now.
丹尼尔
Daniel.
丹尼尔·普莱维，房子着火了！
Daniel Plainview, the house is on fire!
丹尼尔兄弟， 是我，伊莱
Brother Daniel, it's Eli.
是你，是你啊
Yes, it is. Yes, it is.
来杯酒吧
I'll make us a drink.
你的家真是个奇迹
Your home is a miracle.
太漂亮了
It's beautiful.
真是太漂亮了
愿主保佑这里
God bless it.
这些日子我一直在各地传道
I've been spreading His word far and wide.
广为传道
Far and wide.
为了主我四处奔波
So much travel for Him.
我还曾通过无线电散播福音
I've been working in radio.
发生了那么多事情…
Yes, so much... So much has been happening.
回来看到你一切都好，我很高兴
To be here and find you and see you well is wonderful.
正好有机会，我们叙叙旧
And we have a chance to catch up.
不用了，谢谢你
No. Thank you so much.
我亲爱的兄弟
My brother.
丹尼尔，我的兄弟，我们是姻亲啊
Daniel, my brother by marriage.
多少年的老朋友…都这么多年了
We're such old friends. So much time.
经历了这么多起起落落…
Things go up, things go down,
至少还有主总在我们身旁
but at least the Lord is always around.
我们有过得意，也有过失意，不是么？
We've seen ups and downs, haven't we?
你现在失意么，伊莱？
Are things down for you right now, Eli?
现在没有
No. No.
但我的确带来了一个悲伤的消息
But I do come with some sad news.
还记得班迪先生么？
Perhaps you remember Mr. Bandy?
他老人家已升入天国了
Mr. Bandy has passed on to the Lord.
他活了99岁，愿神保佑
He lived to be 99 years old, God bless him.
班迪先生有个孙子   他叫威廉，你见过么？
Mr. Bandy has a grandson. Have you met his grandson, William?
威廉班迪是我们最好的兄弟之一…
William Bandy is one of the finest members we have
为第三启示教会奉献了很多
at the Church of the Third Revelation.
他很想去好莱坞拍电影
He's eager to come to Hollywood to be in movies.
他长得不错
He is very good-looking.
- 我觉得他能红   - 那样很好嘛
- And I do think he will have success. - That's wonderful.
要不要我找他谈谈？
Would you like me to speak with him?
丹尼尔，我问你是否愿意…
Daniel, I'm asking if you'd like to have business
和第三启示教会做笔交易
with the Church of the Third Revelation
在小班迪的那一千英亩地上钻井采油
in developing this lease on young Bandy's 1,000-acre tract.
小波士顿的这块地，我可以给你
I'm offering you to drill
面积非常大，还没人开发过！
on one of the great undeveloped fields of Little Boston.
- 我很高兴和你合作   - 你愿意？
- I'd be happy to work with you. - You would?
是是，当然，那样太好了
Yes, yes, of course. That's wonderful.
但我有个条件
But there is one condition for this work.
好吧你说
All right.
我希望你亲口跟我说   你是一个冒牌的先知
I'd like you to tell me that you are a false prophet.
我希望你亲口跟我说   你是，而且从来都是个冒牌的先知
I'd like you to tell me that you are, and have been a false prophet.
所谓的上帝也不过是迷信
And that God is a superstition.
这是谎言
But that's a lie.
这是谎言，我不能说谎
It's a lie. I cannot say it.
- 什么时候开始钻井？   - 很快就能开始
- When can we begin to drill? - Very soon.
那多久之后能开始出油呢？
How long will it take to bring in the well?
不会很久的
lt shouldn't take long.
我要十万美金作为签字费…
I would like a $100,000 signing bonus,
外加先前欠的五千元，还有利息
plus the five that is owed to me with interest.
恩，这样才公平嘛
That's only fair.
我是一个冒牌的先知   上帝是迷信的产物
I am a false prophet, and God is a superstition.
如果你这么认为，我就这么说
If that's what you believe, then I will say it.
- 要用令人信服的语气说出来   - 丹尼尔…
- Say it like you mean it. - Daniel.
要用你布道的口气说
Say it like it's your sermon.
不要笑
Don't smile.
我是一个冒牌的先知
I am a false prophet.
- 上帝是迷信的产物   - 何不站起来说？
- God is a superstition. - Why don't you stand up?
把杯子放下
Put your glass down.
我是一个冒牌的先知
I am a false prophet.
- 上帝是迷信的产物   - 伊莱，停一下
- God is a superstition. - Eli, stop.
把这里想作是你的教堂   面前还坐满了信徒…
Just imagine this is your church here and you have a full congregation, so...
我是一个冒牌的先知   上帝是迷信的产物
I am a false prophet. God is a superstition.
再说一遍
Say it again.
我是一个冒牌的先知   上帝是迷信的产物
I am a false prophet. God is a superstition.
坐在后面的人听不清楚
They can't hear you at the back.
我是一个冒牌的先知   上帝是迷信的产物
I am a false prophet. God is a superstition.
再说一遍
Say it again.
我是一个冒牌的先知！   上帝是迷信的产物！
I am a false prophet! God is a superstition!
再说一遍
Say it again.
我是一个冒牌的先知！   上帝是迷信的产物！
I am a false prophet! God is a superstition!
那片地方的油已经采完了
Those areas have been drilled.
什么？
What?
那些地方的油已经采完了
Those areas, they've been drilled.
- 不，没有   - 是采完了…
- No, they haven't. - Yes, it's...
这就是所谓的抽水效应，伊莱
It's called drainage, Eli.
听着，那农场周围的地都是我的   所以我早把他地下的油给抽干了
See, I own everything around it, so, of course, I get what's underneath it.
那儿连个采油平台都没有
But there are no derricks there.
是班迪的地…知道我说哪儿么？
This is the Bandy tract. Do you understand?
还没明白过来，伊莱？
Do you understand, Eli?
似乎没搞清楚的是你   明白没有？
That's more to the point. Do you understand?
我喝光了你杯子里的水，我把它喝光了
I drink your water. I drink it up every day.
我每天都在吸班迪地皮底下的圣血
I drink the blood of Lamb from Bandy's tract.
现在你可以坐下了
You can sit down again.
哦，丹尼尔
Daniel.
丹尼尔
求你了
Please.
- 我已经无路可走了   - 我知道
- I am in desperate times. - I know.
- 我需要一个朋友   - 是啊，你当然需要了
- I need a friend. - Yes. Of course, you do.
我犯了罪
I've sinned.
我需要帮助，我是罪人
I need help. I'm a sinner.
我做梦也不曾想   竟让魔鬼夺了魂
I've let the devil grab hold of me in ways I never imagined.
我是个不折不扣的罪人
I'm so full of sin.
上帝有时候会考验我们，不是么？
The Lord sometimes challenges us, doesn't He, Eli?
- 哦，丹尼尔，没错…   - 是啊，他会的
- Yes, He does, Daniel. - Yes, He does.
是的，他考验了我啊啊啊！
Yes, He does!
是啊他考验了你啊啊啊啊！
最近的经济大危机   他连一声提醒都没给我…
He's completely failed to alert me to the recent panic in our economy.
- 还有这件事…   - 哦，小可怜
- And this... - Oh, dear.
我必须得弄到钱，丹尼尔   我必须、非得、一定要弄到钱
I must have this, Daniel. I must, I must, I must have this.
我需要这笔钱填补投资黑洞
My investments have...
丹尼尔，我不想烦你，可要是能   抓到主的手乞求帮助，我早去了
Daniel, I won't bore you, but if I could grab the Lord's hand for help I would,
但他总是不吭声…
but He does these things all the time.
故作神秘，让我们干等着…
These mysteries that He presents, and while we wait...
干等着他发话！
While we wait for His word!
因为上帝选中的兄弟不是你，伊莱
Because you're not the chosen brother, Eli.
他选中了你的双胞胎兄弟，保罗
'Twas Paul who was chosen.
是保罗找到我，告诉我到这儿来   你只是个傻子
He found me and told me about your land. You're just a fool.
- 为什么要提起保罗？   - 你兄弟没做到的，我做到了
- Why are you talking about Paul? - I did what your brother couldn't.
- 别跟我说这些   - 我击溃了你，打垮了你
- Don't say this to me. - I broke you and I beat you.
是保罗他告诉我有你这么个人
It was Paul told me about you.
他才是先知，他才是智者   他早知道地底下藏着宝藏
He's the prophet. He's the smart one. He knew what was there
是他找到了我，让我去把宝藏挖出来
and he found me to take it out of the ground.
你知道最有趣的是什么？   听着，听好了…
Know what the funny thing is? Listen, listen.
我给了他一万美元，全是现金   事实就是这样
I paid him $10,000 cash in hand. Just like that.
他现在自己开了家公司   小生意蒸蒸日上
He has his own company now. Prosperous little business.
旗下三口油井，周入五千美金
Three wells producing, $5,000 a week.
你个大哭包，别哭哭啼啼了   我不想再听你胡扯
Stop crying, you sniveling ass. Stop your nonsense.
伊莱，其实你只是你兄弟出生时   顺带落出的那个胎盘
- You're just the afterbirth, Eli. - No.
- 不   - 从你母亲产后的秽物中滑落出来
That slithered out on your mother's filth.
不
No.
他们应该把你装在玻璃瓶里   搁置在壁炉架上
They should've put you in a glass jar on the mantelpiece.
保罗在妈妈身上吸奶的时候，你在哪儿？
Where were you when Paul was suckling at his mother's teat?
你在哪儿啊？
Where were you?
谁把你养大的，可怜的伊莱？   班迪家的一头母猪么？
Who was nursing you, poor Eli? One of Bandy's sows?
那块地我早就吃干净了   对此你一点办法也没有
That land has been had. Nothing you can do about it. It's gone.
- 请你买下这块地皮吧…   - 你输了
- lf you would just take this lease... - You lose.
抽水效应！
Drainage!
知道抽水效应么，伊莱！   你个小毛孩子…
Drainage, Eli, you boy.
我很抱歉，已经抽干了
Drained dry. I'm so sorry.
如果你有一杯奶昔
If you have a milkshake
我也有一杯奶昔…
and I have a milkshake,
我还有一根吸管，就在那儿   那是一根吸管，看到没？
and I have a straw, there it is. That's the straw, you see?
看好了
Watch it.
我的吸管穿过房间…
Now my straw reaches across the room
然后开始喝你的奶昔
and starts to drink your milkshake.
我在喝你的奶昔！
I drink your milkshake!
- 我把它喝光了！   - 丹尼尔，别逼我
- I drink it up! - Don't bully me, Daniel.
就你那破嗓子和烂舞步，还有你   那点迷信就能无往不胜么，伊莱？
Did you think your song and dance and your superstition would help you, Eli?
我才是第三启示！   我才是上帝选中的使者！
I am the Third Revelation. I am who the Lord has chosen.
- 丹尼尔！   - 因为我比你聪明！
- Daniel! - Because I'm smarter than you!
我比你年长！
I'm older!
我是你的老朋友呀，丹尼尔！
I'm your old friend, Daniel!
- 我可不是什么假先知…   - 救命！救命啊！
- I'm not a false prophet... - Help me! Help me!
…你这乳臭未干的娃娃！
...you sniveling boy!
我就是第三启示！   我就是第三启示！
I am the Third Revelation! I am the Third Revelation!
- 我说过要生吃了你！   - 我们是亲人！
- I told you I would eat you. - We're family!
- 我说过要生吞了你！   - 我们是兄弟！是兄弟！
- I told you I would eat you up! - We're brothers! We're brothers!
丹尼尔，请饶了我吧，求你了
Daniel, please forgive me. I beg you.
在那儿，在那儿啊
That's it. That's it.
丹尼尔先生？
Mr. Daniel?
我没事了
I'm finished.